<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Christians comfort In a sermon appointed for the crosse, but preached in S. Pauls Church on Candlemas day, 1623. By Thomas Myriell, rector of S. Steuens in Walbrooke London.</title>
            <author>Myriell, Thomas, d. 1629.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1623</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 86 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 36 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07951</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18321</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103112</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838869</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838869</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3259</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07951)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3259)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1211:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Christians comfort In a sermon appointed for the crosse, but preached in S. Pauls Church on Candlemas day, 1623. By Thomas Myriell, rector of S. Steuens in Walbrooke London.</title>
                  <author>Myriell, Thomas, d. 1629.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 63, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by G.P[urslowe] for Iohn White, and are to bee sold at his shop in little Brittaine, at the signe of the holy Lambe, neere vnto Aldersgate streete,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1623.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3259:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3259:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE CHRISTIANS COMFORT.</p>
            <p>IN A SERMON APPOIN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for the Croſſe, but Preached in S. PAVLS CHVRCH <hi>on Candlemas day,</hi> 1623.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Thomas Myriell,</hi> Rector of <hi>S. Steuens</hi> in
<hi>Walbrooke</hi> LONDON.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1. Ioh. 4.4.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Greater is he that is with vs, then he that is in this world.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Nec plus ad deijciendum poteſt terrena poena, quàm ad erigen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum tutela diuina,</p>
               <bibl>Cyprian.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>G. P.</hi> for <hi>Iohn White,</hi> and are to bee ſold at his Shop in little <hi>Brittaine,</hi> at the ſigne of the holy Lambe, neere vnto <hi>Alderſgate</hi> ſtreete.
1623.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:3259:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3259:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIHGT HONORABLE <hi>PETER Proby,</hi> Lord Maior of LONDON, M<hi rend="sup">r.</hi> 
               <hi>Iohn Hodges,</hi> and Sir <hi>Humphrey Hanford,</hi> Knight, the two Sheriffes of the ſaid City: And to the reſt of the right Worſhipfull Knights and Aldermen; the Maſter, Wardens and <hi>Aſsistants of the right Worſhipfull</hi> Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of the Grocers, my ſingular good
<hi>Patrones, all health and happineſſe in</hi> this world, and that that is to come.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honorable, Right Worſhipfull, &amp;c.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was a ſolemne Law a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Perſians,</hi> that whenſoeuer their King went abroad, ſuch as met him, muſt ſalute him with ſome gift, ſuch as their ſtate and condition beſt <pb facs="tcp:3259:3"/>ſupplyed them withall. The equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of this Law, J ſuppoſe, aroſe from hence, that ſeeing the King is the common Father and Protector of the Countrey, euerie man ſhould ſtriue by the donation of ſome thing, to ſhew his thankefulneſſe vnto him, for that vnſpeakeable benefit. It fell out on a time, that <hi>Artaxerxes,</hi> ſurna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Mnemon,</hi> a famous King of the <hi>Perſians,</hi> being to trauell abroad, was in his way ready to meet one <hi>Sinaetas,</hi> a poore, but honeſt ſubiect, when he was farre from home, and ſo vnprouided of his gift; Which he perceiuing, and being loth to bee found ſlacker then o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in his duty, ranne immediately to the riuer <hi>Cyrus,</hi> and ioyning both his hands together, catched vp a quantity <pb facs="tcp:3259:3"/>of water, which hee brought and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to the King. Which done, the King very graciouſly accepted it, and highly prayſing the mans honeſty for it, commanded forthwith his Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuches to take the water out of his palmes, and put it in a golden Viall to keep. This Story ſomewhat fits my caſe: You are to me next vnder God and his Maieſtie, the meanes of my temporall wel-fare and maintenance; you gaue me freely my Liuing where I feed ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually, and am fed temporally, beſides many other courteſies from time to time receiued. For all which fauours, J haue nothing to retribute backe vnto you, but with <hi>Sinaetas,</hi> to bring you a little water, not from the riuer <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus,</hi> but from the Fountaine of Life, <pb facs="tcp:3259:4"/>the Well of liuing waters, the holy Word of God. And in this kinde I haue ſundry times beene officious to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards you, but it was neuer put vp in a Viall till now, but as water in the hand, by drops ſhed and ſpilt againe on the ground. This I haue preſumed to put vp my ſelfe, not without the requeſt and deſire of many others, that there might remaine hereafter ſome eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of thankefull acknowledgement on my part, for your many fauours. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it therefore, I beſeech you, and take it kindly, as coming from him, whoſe minde is willing to expreſſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe towards you in the moſt thankeful manner. And J deſire you to reade it without preiudice and partiality, as it was vttered by me in all plainneſſe and <pb facs="tcp:3259:4"/>ſyncerity. J doubt not, but ſuch will find content in it, who haue learned to iudge of a Preacher, not by ſtooping ſo low, as to meaſure him by outward po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pularity, but by looking into him, and weighing him by ſelfe-ſufficiency. Jn which hope, I reſt, and for this time humbly take leaue, praying the God of all mercy, to direct all your endeuorus to his glory, and the flouriſhing wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare of the whole Company.</p>
            <closer>
               <date>
                  <hi>Feb. 24. 1622.</hi>
               </date>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Yours in all the ſeruices</hi> of loue and duty,
<hi>THOMAS MYRIELL.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:3259:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:3259:5"/>
            <head>THE CHRISTIANS COMFORT.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Text. <hi>2. Chron. 15.2.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>The Lord is with you, while ye be with him; and if ye ſeeke him, he will be found of you; but if ye forſake him, he will forſake you.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F it were lawfull to aſſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late heauenly verities to earthly fictions, I would compare my Text to the three Graces. For the parts of it are naturally three, as is their number<note n="a" place="margin">Pauſan. Baetic. lib. <hi>9.</hi> Senec. de Benef. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap.
<hi>3.</hi>
               </note> and as they hold together hand in hand, ſo doe theſe depend each on other: and as their ſite and place is ſo ordered, that
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:3259:6"/>for one turning from you, you haue two loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king towards you; iuſt ſo it is here. And laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as they two firſt looke towards you, before the third turne from you; ſo here, two parts firſt behold vs kindly:
<hi>The Lord is with you, while ye be with him; and if ye ſeeke him, he will be found of you.</hi> And the third turnes from vs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, but not till we turne from it; <hi>If ye forſake him, he will forſake you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Text highly to be valued, for the Author who ſpeakes it,
<hi>Azariah</hi> a famous Prophet; for the auditors who heard it, King
<hi>Aſa,</hi> and all <hi>Iuda</hi> and <hi>Beniamin;</hi> for the occaſion that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured it, a great deliuerance from an vnſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able danger: and principally for the matter contained in it, being ſuch as may comfort the weake, terrifie the wicked, ſtay the wauering, and ſtir vp the backeward, to draw neere vnto God by repentance, and amendment of life.</p>
            <p>It is deuided to my hand: The parts three, but each admitting ſeuerall partitions, as wee ſhall heare; the firſt in theſe words,
<hi>The Lord is with you, while ye be with him.</hi> Wherein conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der 2. things. 1. The comfort. 2. The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition. <pb n="3" facs="tcp:3259:6"/>The comfort,
<hi>Dominus vobiſcum: The Lord is with you.</hi> The condition, <hi>Si fueritis<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> cum eo: while ye are with him.</hi> For the firſt.</p>
            <p>This ſweet ſaying <hi>Dominus vobiſcum,</hi> may bee taken as a Prayer, or as a promiſe. As a Prayer, and then it ſhewes the Paſtor his hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty deſire for the good of men; for a promiſe, and then it cheares vp the people to the feruent ſeruice of God. The firſt way it is ancient and generall. Ancient, an ordinary ſalutation in the Iewiſh Church,
<hi>Ruth</hi> 2.4. <hi>Iud.</hi> 6.12.<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Such as among vs, GOD ſaue you, or GOD ſpeed: not deſeruing to bee termed, Short cuts, or ſhreddings, as the great Cutter of our Church<note n="b" place="margin">T. C. <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>pag.</hi>
138.</note> hath vnmannerly termed them; but hearty and pithie expreſſions of our vnfained charity one towards another. Generall againe it is: for it was vſed in the Church, in <hi>Cyprian</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Vid. Boy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> par. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note>, and
<hi>Tertullians</hi> time, in the Liturgie of S. <hi>Iames</hi> and
<hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> &amp;c. and continued in the Church to this very day. Conſiſting of few words in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, but including abundant matter; Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as<note n="d" place="margin">Ioh. Trit. in Dam.</note> 
               <hi>Petrus Damianus</hi> is reported to haue written a whole booke of it, intituled, <hi>Dominus vobiſcum.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:3259:7"/>
            <p>Take it as a promiſe, and ſo we muſt in this place, if we take it aright, and then it is the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets Alarum to incourage the hearts of the people againſt their enemies, and may ſerue to cheare vp all the faithfull againſt the malice of the whole world. For, <hi>Si Deus nobiſcum, quis contranos?</hi> Rom. 8. 31. If God bee with vs, who can be againſt vs? and as <hi>Cyprian,</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Cyp. de o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat. Dom.</note>
               <hi>Quis ei de ſeculo metus eſt, cui Deus in ſeculo tutor eſt?</hi> What needs hee feare the malice of the world, who hath God his protector in the middeſt of the world?</p>
            <p>To procede aright, conſider in this defence the author who, and the manner how hee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fends. The Author, <hi>Dominus, The Lord.</hi> A name too great to bee claſped in the marrow palme of our apprehenſion. <hi>Eſt enim hoc Dei cogno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> ſaith <hi>Tertullian</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Tert. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pol. cap. <hi>34.</hi>
               </note> For this name Sir, is Gods Sir-name. And if <hi>Dominus, quaſi dans munus,</hi> Lord, from Lordly liberalitie; who deſerues the name but hee, <hi>qui dat eſſe, &amp; eſcam,</hi> who giues life and liuing to man and beaſt? If poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion make a Lord, Heauen and earth, and all Kingdomes are his; If power, hee can with a <pb n="5" facs="tcp:3259:7"/>breath make &amp; vnmake ten thouſand worlds; If multitude of ſeruants, this Lord of Hoaſtes hath his armies in heauen, earth and hell; If valiant ſoldiours, he hath millions of millions that haue dyed for him; inſomuch as if ſome are not miſtaken<note n="g" place="margin">Pet. de Natal.</note>, there is neuer a day in the yeere but may challenge eight or nine thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Martyrs, who haue died in their Maſters quarrell. Finally, the enioying of his owne will,
<hi>Pſal.</hi> 135.6. working all things after his owne counſell,
<hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.11. and all this with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out intermiſſion, or interciſion, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10.16 proues him ſufficiently, not onely a Lord, but the onely Lord.</p>
            <p>And this is the reaſon that many famous Emperours refuſed it, as too high a name. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtus Imperij formator,</hi> ſaith
<hi>Tertullian</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Tert-A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polo, cap.
<hi>34.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ne Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minum quidem diciſe volebat. Auguſtus</hi> the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Romane Empire (for his father <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar</hi> was but
<hi>Metator,</hi> rather then <hi>Imperator</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Oroſ. lib. <hi>7.</hi> cap. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> the chalker of it out, then the ſetter of it vp) This great man would not be called Lord. And of the ſame mind was <hi>Alexander Seuerus</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Lamprid. in Alex.</note>, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. And no Emperour affected it till <hi>Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian</hi> 
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:3259:8"/>came, who was ſo likoriſh of tranſcendent highneſſe, that hee called himſelfe God too. <hi>Dominus &amp; Deus noſter Domitianus</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Suet. in Dominion.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c.</hi> A true forerunner of his ſucceſſor the Pope, who in the Extrauagants<note n="l" place="margin">Extra. <hi>Ioh. 22.</hi> cap. Cum inter. in gloſ.</note>, (and well it deſerues to be put there) is ſtiled <hi>Dominus Deus noſter Papa;</hi> Our Lord God the Pope.</p>
            <p>Yet what theſe men vnlawfully vſurpe, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers lawfully receiue from him, euen by his owne gift. For he that ſaid, <hi>Ego dixi, Dij eſtis, Pſal.</hi> 82.6. I haue ſaid yee are Gods; deriuing his owne title to the great Ones of the world, hath alſo ſaid, <hi>Ego dixi Domini eſtis,</hi> I haue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed you dominion &amp; Lordſhip in my ſtead, And, <hi>Dicam planè Imperatorem Dominum,</hi> ſaith <hi>Tertullian</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Tert. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pol. cap. <hi>34.</hi>
               </note>, <hi>ſed more communi.</hi> I will call the Emperour Lord, but in the common phraſe, when I am not conſtrained thereby to preiu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice the honour of my Lord God. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there is no ſuch reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that our Reformers ſhould except againſt the reuerend Prelates of the Church, for accepting the name of Lord, bequeathed vnto them by religious deuotion. For in two things they goe before other men; <pb n="7" facs="tcp:3259:8"/>in dignity and grauity: and in two things they muſt be reſpected of vs, in honour and reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence. For which cauſe authority diuine and humane hath giuen them two titles, Lord and Father; Lord, to ſhew their dignity; Father, to expreſſe their grauity. Art not thou my Lord <hi>Elias,</hi> ſaith good <hi>Obadiah?</hi> 1. <hi>King.</hi> 18.7. O my Father, my Father, ſaith <hi>Elizeus</hi> of the ſame, 2. <hi>King.</hi>
2.12.</p>
            <p>Neither neede they feare St. <hi>Peter</hi> his
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.3. ſeeing they make a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall Hierarchy, not a temporall Tyranny: or to vſe S. <hi>Aug.</hi> his phraſe<note n="n" place="margin">Aug. de ciuit. lib. <hi>19.</hi> cap.
<hi>14.</hi>
               </note>; ſeeing they Lord it, <hi>non dominandi ſuperbia: ſed officio conſulendi,</hi> ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the rule of good counſel, then the loue of ſoueraignty; and ſhew themſelues Fathers, <hi>non principandi ſuperbia: ſed prouidendi miſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordia</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Aug.</hi> ibid.</note>, not ſo much in a proud commanding, as in a prouident mildneſſe. And as <hi>Leo</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">Leo Epiſt. <hi>84.</hi> cap. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note>, <hi>Cum plus agat cohortatio, quàm commotio, plus charitas, quàm poteſtas:</hi> They doe more by exhortation of the mouth, then coercition of the hand: and compaſſion, not compulſion, is their chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt attendant.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:3259:9"/>
            <p>But ſee how wee are falne from heauen to earth! Returne we to our great Lord againe, and let vs heare him ſpeaking and pleading vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs,
<hi>Malac.</hi> 1.6. <hi>Si Dominus ego ſum, vbi timor?</hi> If I be a Lord, where is my feare? Certainely a Lord beares relation to a ſeruant, &amp; a ſeruants badge is feare. He hath bin to vs a Father and a Lord too: if we will not loue him as Sonnes, yet at leaſt let vs feare him as ſeruants; Eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly conſidering, his ſeruice procures both dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and commodity. Honour and profit, the two great baytes of humane affections attend vpon it. Honour it brings, <hi>Deo ſeruire, regna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re eſt:</hi> to ſerue God, is to raigne as a King: and <hi>Philo</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">Phil. lib. de regno.</note>, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> To ſerue God, is better not onely then liberty or freedome, but a Kingdome or Soueraign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. And ſo commodity it brings too: for by ſeruing this Lord, wee are ſaued from all ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.
<hi>Auguſtine</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Aug. de eiuit. Dei, lib.
<hi>19.</hi> cap. <hi>15.</hi>
               </note> well notes, <hi>Seruus</hi> comes
<hi>à ſeruando,</hi> a ſeruant, from being preſerued; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe,
<hi>Quiiure belli poſſent occidi, a victoribus ſeruabantur.</hi> Such as by right of warre might haue beene ſlaine, by the mercy of their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querors
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:3259:9"/>were kept aliue. So it was a mutuall pact <hi>Serua &amp; ſeruia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> Preſerue thou me, &amp; I will be thy ſeruant. And is not this our caſe? or is it our caſe, &amp; ſhal it not be our duty? Let vs heare <hi>Zachary,</hi> &amp; he wiltel vs, That we being deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from our enemies,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.74.</note> might ſerue him in righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe and holines all the dayes of our life.</p>
            <p>O then, why doe we not humbly ſerue this great LORD, but proudly ſtriue againſt him? what intolerable impudence is it for men to vſe him as they doe? Some giue him the lie, by vnbeliefe; others the ſtab, by ſwearing &amp; blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheming; many giue him the Brauado, by an audacious contradicting his ſettled truth; and ſome the flout, by laughing at the miſeries of his Church. Is this to make our ſelues his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, to accompt him as a Lord?. who dares vſe his Maſter ſo? Who will ſay to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> King, Thou art wicked? &amp; to Princes, Ye are vngod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly? <hi>Iob</hi> 34.18. Oh how much leſſe ſhould they ſay it to him, who accepteth not the perſon of Princes, nor regardeth the rich more then the poore! <hi>S. Peter</hi> 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.18 bids ſeruants obey their Maſters, though they be froward, much
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:3259:10"/>more if they be milde. How then ſhould we be pliant to this great Lord, conſidering he is euer mercifull and kinde, or as it is in my text, <hi>Nobiſcum;</hi> euer with vs to helpe and ſuccour vs? And this is the ſecond thing in this Promiſe, the manner how he defends vs,
<hi>viz.</hi> by being with vs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Is with you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is true, that God is with all men, and that in all places, and at all times: but he is eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with his Children and ſeruants, and euer for ſome good, for ſome ſingular comfort. For as in beauen our happineſſe is to be with him; ſo on earth our welfare is, that he is with vs.</p>
            <p>And God is with vs in two reſpects. 1. For our ſpirituall, 2. for our temporall eſtates. For our ſpiritual eſtates, St.
<hi>Auguſt.</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Aug. de verb. Apoſt. ſerm.
<hi>16.</hi>
               </note> obſerues, God is with
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 4. waies; 1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> he is with vs, <hi>vt praede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtineret nos,</hi> for our predeſtination to life. 2 He is with vs, <hi>vt vocaret nos,</hi> at and in our vocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on on to grace. 3. He is with vs, <hi>vt iuſtificaret nos,</hi> at and for our iuſtification from ſinne 4. He is with vs, <hi>vt glorificaret nos,</hi> for our glorification in heauen<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> He predeſtinated vs before we were <pb n="11" facs="tcp:3259:10"/>our ſelues; he called vs, when we were depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from our ſelues; he iuſtified vs when wee were ſinfull, &amp; he glorified vs, when we were mortall. More he could not adde, to raiſe vs to royall happines; leſſe he could not doe, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue vs from reall miſery. Vpon this <hi>Paul</hi> ſhouts in a triumph; <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.31. If God be with vs, who can
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e againſt vs? or if againſt vs, how can he ouercome vs? Man (he is an inferiour enemy) cannot bring vs to death, for God hath predeſtinated vs to life. The world (that is an exteriour enemy) cannot allure vs from God, for God hath called vs to himſelfe. The fleſh (that is an interiour enemy) cannot driue vs to ſinne, for God hath iuſtified vs by Chriſt. The Diuell (he is a ſuperior enemy) cannot damne vs in hell, for God hath glorified vs in heauen.
<hi>Nemo nos laedit, niſi qui Deum vincit,</hi> ſaith
<hi>Anſel.</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">Anſ. in Rom. <hi>8.31.</hi>
               </note> we are in good caſe, our ſoules are ſafe, no man can hurt vs, but he which can ouercome euen God himſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, for our temporall eſtates, God is with vs there too; and that either to defend vs in time of aduerſity, as God was with <hi>Ioſeph</hi> in <pb n="12" facs="tcp:3259:11"/>the priſon, <hi>Gen.</hi>
39.21. or to aduance vs in time of proſperity, as God was with <hi>Dauid</hi> in <hi>Sauls</hi> Court;<note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 16.18.</note> or generally to proſper with hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py ſucceſſe all our actions, and to incline vnto vs all mens affections, as God was with <hi>Iohn Baptiſt, Luk.</hi> 1.66. Take it how you will, eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one of theſe waies God was with King <hi>Aſa,</hi> as <hi>Azariah</hi> heretels him. Firſt,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d was with him to proſper his handy worke, for hee built fenced Cities in <hi>Iuda,</hi> and the land had reſt and peace, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 14.6 Secondly, he not onely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended him againſt an inuincible army, ſuch as I thinke was neuer heard of in the world be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, an hoaſt of a thouſand thouſand men; but aduanced him &amp; inriched him with their ſpoyles, whileſt he ſacked, and ranſacked their glorious tents, and carried away innumerable ſpoiles into his owne Country. Thus the Lord was with him, and be proſpered accordingly.</p>
            <p>Would any man be happy in his labour? Let him goe to worke
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> As <hi>Peter</hi> laboured all night and caught nothing, becauſe Chriſt was not with him, <hi>Luk.</hi> 5.5. ſo many ſweat and toyle, and ſtriue in the ſea of this world, and <pb n="13" facs="tcp:3259:11"/>catch nothing, becauſe God is not with them. If God be with thee, euery thing ſhall goe well with thee; yea, if God be with thee, it matters not what, nor where thou be: wert thou with <hi>Samſon</hi> enuironed with an army of
<hi>Philiſtines,</hi> if the Lord be with thee, thou ſhalt deſtroy the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all. Wert thou with the three children in an hot fierie furnace, if the Lord bee with thee, thou ſhalt come out vnſinged. Wert thou with <hi>Ionas</hi> in the Whales belly, if the Lord bee with thee, thou ſhalt be caſt ſafe on the land againe. Wert thou with <hi>Daniel</hi> in the Lyons den, if the Lord be with thee, thou ſhalt not be touched. Wert thou with <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> in chaines in the darke dungeon, if the Lord be with thee, thou ſhalt be ſet at liberty. Wert thou with <hi>Iohn</hi> in the Caldron of ſcalding oyle, if God be with thee, thou ſhalt come out vnhurt. What will not Gods preſence doe for vs? To what will it not aduance vs?
<hi>Eſther</hi> was rayſed from a cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue to a Queene, for God was with her, <hi>Eſt.</hi> 5.2. <hi>Dauid</hi> promoted <hi>a pedo ad ſceptrum,</hi> from the ſheephooke to the Scepter, for God was with him,
<hi>Pſal.</hi> 78.71. <hi>Ioſeph</hi> ſet vp from a priſoner at
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:3259:12"/>the bar, to a Magiſtrate on the bench, for God was with him, <hi>Gen.</hi> 41.43. <hi>Elizeus</hi> changed, <hi>ab ar atore, in orator om,</hi> from a Plowman, to a Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher, for God was with him, 1.
<hi>King.</hi> 19.20. The Apoſtles were made, <hi>ex piſcatoribus, Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcopi,</hi> of fiſhermen, fiſhers of men, for God was with them;
<hi>Mat.</hi> 4.19. Finally, as Philoſophy told <hi>Seneca</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">Senec. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. <hi>41.</hi>
               </note>, <hi>Bonus vir fine Deo nemo eſt.</hi> No man can be good without God. So Chriſtiani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty tels vs,
<hi>Beatus vir ſine Deo nemo eſt.</hi> No man can be proſperous without God.</p>
            <p>And therefore let this <hi>Dominus nobiſcum,</hi> be our
<hi>Panchreſtum,</hi> a medicine for all maladies; when wee come to preach, let <hi>Dominus nobiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum</hi> take vp the text; when you come to heare, let
<hi>Dominus vobiſcum</hi> prepare your attention; whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you go forth, let
<hi>Dominus vobiſcu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> be your <hi>vadè meoum,</hi> and inſeparable aſſociate; when you part with your friends and ſeruants to ſea, ſay <hi>Dominus vobiſcum,</hi> for a Pilot to waft them. To conclude, as St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Aug. ad Valer. Epiſt. <hi>77.</hi>
               </note> ſaid of his <hi>Deo gratius,</hi> Thankes be to God; ſo I of my <hi>Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus vobiſcum,</hi> The Lord be with you. <hi>Hoc nec dici breuius, nec audiri laetius, nec intelligi grandius,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:3259:12"/>nec agi fructuoſius poteſt.</hi> This thing is ſuch, that nothing can bee ſaid more briefly, nothing heard more gladly, nothing vnderſtood more largely, nothing done more fruitfully.</p>
            <p>O but, ſay ſome, how ſhall I gaine him? how ſhall I bee made partaker of this rich treaſure? My text tells you in the next words,
<hi>Dominus vobiſcum, ſi fueritis cum eo:</hi> The Lord is with you, if you be with him; and that is the ſecond member of this firſt part.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
               <hi>If you be with him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If we be with him. Why how can that bee? God is in heauen, we on the earth, <hi>Eceles.</hi> 5.2. How can earth flie vp into heauen to be with God? True, therefore God comes down from heauen to dwel with earth,
<hi>Pſal.</hi> 113.6. though his dwelling be in heauen, yet hee humbleth himſelfe to behold the things in heauen and in earth. What is meant by beholding, but dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling? by heauen &amp; earth, but a righteous man? ſaith
<hi>Auguſtine</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">Auguſt in Pſal.
<hi>112.</hi>
               </note>, who is Heauen <hi>propter ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritus libertatem,</hi> for the libertie of the ſpirit; and earth, <hi>propter corporis ſeruitutem,</hi> for the ſerui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of the body. Now hee with whom God
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:3259:13"/>dwels, is certainely with God; and ſo wee are with him, becauſe he is with vs.</p>
            <p>More plainely, two waies a man is ſaid to be with God, <hi>in intellectu &amp; affectu,</hi> in the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding and iudgement; and with the will &amp; affections. In our vnderſtanding, when we know him; in our affectinos, when wee loue him. But both theſe muſt goe together, to be perfectly with God, <hi>Non enim potes</hi> ſaith <hi>S. Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard<note n="z" place="margin">Bernard.</note> aut amare quem non nouerit, aut habere que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> non amaueris,</hi> Thou canſt: not either loue him whom thou doeſt not know, or inioy him whom thou doeſt not loue.</p>
            <p>Firſt therefor, we are with him, if we know him; and from him, if we know him not. Not that wee can perfectly know him, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore cannot perfectly be with him. That we cannot perfectly know him, the ſharpeſt wits haue confeſſed. <hi>Triſmegiſtus</hi> among other titles called him
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> that is, as <hi>Lactantius</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> de ira Dei, lib. <hi>8.</hi> cap. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounds it, <hi>Tantus, vt ab bomine not poſsit aut ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis enarrari, aut ſenſibus aſtimari,</hi> So great that he can neither be expreſſed in words, nor concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued in thought. And as <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Aug. lib. de cog. ver. vit. &amp; de verb. Dom. ſerm. <hi>38.</hi>
               </note> ſweetly, The
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:3259:13"/>beſt part of our knowledge is, rather to know what hee is not, then what hee is. For as a cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Statue or forme is compoſed &amp; brought into perfection by hewing and cutting ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſtill from it, not by adding any thing vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it: ſo this great Lord is knowne of vs, by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying him ſuch and ſuch like things as are common to the creatures, and by
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ing away humane conceits from him, wher<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to conceiue what he is.</p>
            <p>But though we know him not wholy as he is in himſelfe, yet we may &amp; muſt know him holily as he is in his Word. For as the King is knowne what hee is by his Lawes, ſo God is perceiued who he is by his Will; neither is any man ſo farre from God, as he which knowes not his Word and Commandement.</p>
            <p>And thus two ſorts of men are ſeuered from God; the ignorant, and the erroneous. The ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant; for ſuch are not with God, they are they know not where; God dwels in light, but the ignorant man is in darkeneſſe, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he is ſaid to grope, <hi>Act.</hi> 17.27. In this caſe were all wee before Chriſt came, and all Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens <pb n="18" facs="tcp:3259:14"/>thens now vnto who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Chriſt is not yet come. They are not in this world with God, but they are with the god of this world. And the god of this world is the Diuell in the world to come, who ſhall puniſh them for not knowing the true God that made them. Ignorance, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ther it be a ſin, as in ſuch as might know, or a puniſhment of ſinne, as in ſuch as could not know, it is in both, not <hi>iuſta excuſatio,</hi> but<note n="c" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. ad Sixt. Epiſt.
<hi>105.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>iuſta damnatio;</hi> no iuſt excuſall at the barre of Gods iudgement, but a iuſt refuſal from the ioyes of Heauen.</p>
            <p>And as bad or vvorſe is the erroneous man: For he wilfully goes out of the way, when the hand poynts him to the true path. Hee is not vvith God, for God is truth, and he is run mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding with the many-headed monſter, Errour. How many by a peruerſeneſſe of iudgement, think they are with Chriſt, when they be with Antichriſt? that ſuppoſe they bee with the Church of God, when they are with the Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue of Satan? that imagine they bee vvith Ieſus, when they are with the Ieſuits? that hope they are in the gates of heauen, when they bee <pb n="19" facs="tcp:3259:14"/>in the mouth of hell?
<hi>Sulpitius Seuerus</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">in vit. S. Martin. lib.
<hi>1.</hi>
               </note> tels a ſtory, That neer the Citie where S. <hi>Martin</hi> ſate, there was a religious place much frequented, on it an Altar built, at it much deuotion vſed, becauſe as vvas thought, certain Martyrs there had ſuffered for the name of Chriſt. S. <hi>Martin</hi> being troubled that he knew not vvhat Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs they were, after hee had abſtained for a vvhile from the place, at time conuenient hee repaired thither, and fell a praying to God, that he would declare vvho and vvhat Martyrs theſe were, vvhoſe renowne had ſo famouſed that frequent place. At laſt, there ſtarts out a ghoſt of a gaſtly and griſly aſpect, and tels him his name and his condition,
<hi>Latronem ſe fuiſſe ob ſcelera percuſſum,</hi> That he vvas no Saint, but a ſinner, not of the company of Martyrs, but murderers;
<hi>cùm illos gloria, ſe poena retineret,</hi> ſeeing they were in glory and happineſſe, he in paine and torment. Thus this credulous peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple thought they vvere with God, or ſome Saint, vvhen they vvere vvith the Diuell and a Theefe.</p>
            <p>May wee not iuſtly thinke our Romaniſh <pb n="20" facs="tcp:3259:15"/>
               <hi>Samaritanes</hi> in the ſame danger, vvho worſhip they know not what? That thinke by their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uotion they do ſeruice to heauen, vvhen. it may be, their Saint to whom they be deuoted, is in hell. And then as their
<hi>Canus</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>Lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 5.
<hi>quae.</hi> 5. <hi>con.</hi> 3.</note> tels them, <hi>Nihil refert Diabolum colas, an hominem condemnatum,</hi> It is all one, to vvorſhip the diuell &amp; a damned ſoule. I vvil not lay this to their charge, though ſome of their owne miſtruſt it, nor vvill I ſay they vvorſhip ſome theef, though Antichriſt be the greateſt theefe in the vvorld, robbing God of his honour, Chriſt of his office, the Church of the Scripture, Chriſts Saints of their liues: but thus much I ſay, they are not where they ſay they are, for they are in error &amp; blindneſſe, vvhen they boaſt they be in light and verity.</p>
            <p>And this is ſo much more in excuſable, by how much they ſhut their eyes againſt the light, and like the <hi>Iewes</hi> put from them the vvords of eternall life, <hi>Act.</hi> 13.46. For the learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; though they cannot but ſee many of their errours, yet as <hi>Pliny</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Plin. lib. <hi>5.</hi> cap. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> ſaid of ſome ſuch like, <hi>Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor antiae pudore mentiri non piget;</hi> being aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to be found ignorant, they are not afraid <pb n="21" facs="tcp:3259:15"/>to lie. And for the vnlearned, the Ieſuiticall blinde obedience hath made them bold to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe all light of moſt holy truth; inſomuch as they will neither be vvith God that made the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, nor their Countrey that bred them, nor the Church that begat them, nor their friends that are neere them, nor their Soueraigne that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tects them.</p>
            <p>But for our ſelues: ſeeing God is vvith vs by preaching, let vs be with him by practice; no place of the vvorld, where God ſhines ſo bright as in <hi>England;</hi> no place of <hi>England,</hi> like
<hi>London;</hi> no place of <hi>London,</hi> like this; this is
<hi>Bethel,</hi> the Houſe of God; here haue you the choyſeſt vvits, the graueſt heads, the ſharpeſt iudgements, continually emptying themſelues vnto you, that vvhoſoeuer comes in among you, may truely fal dovvne in admiration, and ſay, <hi>Now verily God is in you indeed.</hi> 1.
<hi>Corinth.</hi> 14.25.</p>
            <p>Secondly, men are vvith God in affection, and by no affection ſo much as by loue; the ſoule is rather vvhere it loueth, then vvhere it liueth. And ſo that ſoule vvhich loueth God, <pb n="22" facs="tcp:3259:16"/>is wholy with him in heauen, whileſt the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy is on earth. It is true that
<hi>Auguſtine</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Aug. de ciu. Dei, lib.
<hi>14.</hi> cap. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> notes, that <hi>Recta voluntas,</hi> is
<hi>bonus amor,</hi> an vpright will is a good loue, and loue is the Maſter of the affections, yea the ſumme of them, for they are all reduced to that; for loue, when it longs for the thing loued, <hi>cupiditas eſt,</hi> is then deſire; and when it hath the thing it loues, <hi>laetitia eſt,</hi> it is then ioy; On the contrary, when it flies from the thing it affects not,
<hi>timor eſt,</hi> then it is feare; &amp; when it feeles the thing it deſires not, <hi>triſtitia eſt,</hi> it is ſadneſſe. Thus all the affections deſire, ioy, feare, &amp; griefe, are included in loue. So then, if we loue God, we wil deſire to enioy him, ſaying, <hi>Cupio diſſolui et eſſe cum Chriſto, Phil.</hi> 1.23. I deſire to bee diſſolued, and to bee with Chriſt. And hauing enioyed him, wee will reioyce to keepe him, ſaying, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4.6. Lord, lift vp the light of thy countenance vpon me. This is more ioy to men, then wicked men haue, when their corne and Wine and oyle is increaſed. And hauing ſo kept him wee will feare to loſe him, crying, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27.9. Hide not thy face from mee: put not thy ſeruant a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvay <pb n="23" facs="tcp:3259:16"/>in diſpleaſure. And feeling him leaue vs, vve will grieue at his abſence, with this lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, <hi>Pſal.</hi>
22.9. My God, my God, why haſt thou forſaken me?</p>
            <p>Thus then by loue we are with God: chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie is a bond, yea the bond of perfection, which linketh vs to God, and God to vs; we are vvith him, if we loue him; from him, if we loue him not; and loue him we cannot, if vvee loue any thing before him, any thing beſide him, any thing beyond him. We loue ſomthing before him, when vve preferre any thing to him; vve loue ſomething beſide him, vvhen wee ioyne any thing with him; vve loue ſomthing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond him, vvhen wee ioy more in it, then in him. Therefore
<hi>Auguſtine</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Aug. de doct. Chriſt. lib.
<hi>1.</hi> cap. <hi>22.</hi>
               </note> expounds the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, Thou ſhalt loue the Lord thy God, with all thy heart, with all thy ſoule, with all thy ſtrength, of ſupereminent and ouerflowing loue; <hi>Vt ſi quid aliud diligendum venerit in ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum, illuc rapiatur, quo totius dilectionis impetuss currit:</hi> That if any other thing offers it ſelfe to be loued of vs, it ſhould be carried along, and made to runne together with vs to the loue of
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:3259:17"/>God. This is ſpiritually to bee with him in ſoule in this world, that ſoule and body may be eternally with him in the World to come.</p>
            <p>O then, the miſery of vncharitable ſinners! who are ſo hard-hearted that they care not for God, neither is God in all their thoughts,
<hi>Pſal.</hi> 13. That ſay vnto God, Depart from vs, for we regard not the knowledge of thy Lawes, <hi>Iob</hi> 22.17. Amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g which is the ambitious man that dotes vpon Courtlike preferment; the proud man, that purſues glorious titles &amp; vain applauſe; the luxurious man, that ſets the fleſh before the Spirit; the inconſtant man, that changes his religion with the time; But prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally the couetous man, who is onely with his money, &amp; makes that his God, and whoſe heauie bags, and cram'd cheſt preſſeth downe his ſoule, euen as low as hell it ſelfe. I reade in the life of Saint
<hi>Anthony</hi> of <hi>Padua</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Alfonſo Villegas in vita.</note>, a late Saint of the Popes coyning, That he preaching at a rich mans funerall on this text, <hi>Where your treaſure is, there will your heart bee,</hi> added in the end, This text is fulfilled in this couetous man, who making his money his treaſure, had <pb n="25" facs="tcp:3259:17"/>his heart ſtolne away from Almighty God. Certaine perſons preſently going to his Cheſt to open it, found there his heart, as freſh as if it had been newly taken out of a mans breſt. I preſſe no man in this company to beleeue this, but I preſume, many men in this company wil moralize this, hauing hearts not mounting to God by the loue of heauen; but glued to the earth by loue of money, who when they haue done all, can get but <hi>Simon Magus</hi> his portion; they and their money muſt periſh together. Take heede then, Be with God in your deſires and affection, and hee will be with you in his benediction and bleſſing. Thus hauing fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed the handling of this firſt part: Come we to the ſecond, yet not forgetting to pray <hi>Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus nobiſcum</hi> in this alſo; It muſt not leaue vs euen to the end.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And if ye ſeeke him, he will be found of you, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this comes by way of anſwere to a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret queſtion, which ſome might make. You ſay, God is with vs, if we be with him; &amp; with him we be, if we know him and loue him: But how ſhal we come to know him, that we may <pb n="26" facs="tcp:3259:18"/>come to loue him, and ſo be with him? The anſwere is, By ſeeking him: <hi>If ye ſeeke him, he will be found of you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this pleaſe you to conſider 2. things. Firſt, The worke.
2. The wages. The worke, To ſeek God. The wages, The finding of him. The firſt intending to the laſt, and the laſt inuiting to the firſt. For our promiſe of finding him, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiteth vs to the worke of ſeeking him.</p>
            <p>For the firſt, to ſeeke God: It is true, that in this world wee are all at a loſſe: for hauing all ſinned, wee are depriued of the glorie of God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.23. It came to paſſe with <hi>Adam,</hi> as with a griping Vſurer, who extorting more then is due, loſeth principall and intereſt both: for <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> by ſtruing to know more then was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed him, loſt that knowledge which before was granted him; and ſo became ignorant of God, and ignorant of himſelfe. For as a man that is in the darke, cannat ſee any thing, no not himſelfe: So <hi>Adams</hi> heires being borne in ſinne, which is the thickeſt darknes, are igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, and ſee not either God their Creator, or themſelues his creatures.</p>
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:3259:18"/>
            <p>Hence it is, that there is continuall ſeeking vp and downe in the world; ſo that if a queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were made, what all the men in the world doe; it might be anſwered in a word, <hi>Quaerunt,</hi> they are buſie in ſeeking: ſomewhat we want, ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what we would haue, though when wee haue it, we are not contented with it, vntill we finde that which is able to ſatisfie vs, that is, God himſelfe. <hi>A te Domine ſumus, et irrequietum eſt cor noſtrum, donec reuertamur ad te,</hi> ſaith S.
<hi>Auguſtine</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Auguſt. confeſ. lib.</note>, From thee (O Lord) we be, and our hearts are neuer at quiet, till wee bee with thee againe.</p>
            <p>Now for the finding this bleſſed God, which will make an end of all our ſeeking, ſundry things are neceſſary to know, which if they be not vnderſtood, may occaſion vs to loſe all our labour. For, three waies, ſaith <hi>Bernard,</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">Beruard in Cant. ſer. <hi>75.</hi>
               </note> men may be fruſtrated in ſeeking, <hi>Cùm non in tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re quaerunt, aut nen ſicut oportet, vel non vbi opor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tet.</hi> Either if men ſeeke not in due time, or ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, in a right manner, or thirdly, in a fit place.</p>
            <p>For the firſt, We muſt ſeeke him in due time,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:3259:19"/>
               <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.6. <hi>Seeke the Lord while he may be found, call vpon him while he is nigh.</hi> Signifiying, that <hi>Erit proculdubio cùm inueniri non poterit,</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Bernard, vt ſupra.</note> There will bee a time, when hee cannot bee found, &amp; that is, when this life is ended. Now is the acceptable time, now is the day of ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.1. Thou maiſt put it off, if thou wilt, <hi>Et expectato ſalutem in medio Gehennae, quae facta eſt in medio terrae,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bern. ibid.</note> and waite for ſaluation in the midſt of hell, which was wrought for thee in the midſt of the earth. When this life hath an end, then our ſeeking hath an end; and if we finde not here, wee ſhall be ſure to miſſe hereafter. It is neither Hell, nor Purgatory, nor the Graue that can put vs in any hope of finding God. Here if wee miſſe, we miſſe for euer.</p>
            <p>O poore ſeduced <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> why ſhould you thinke to finde God in Purgatorie, when yet the wiſeſt men of the Church could neuer find that there is any Purgatory? When <hi>Chriſoſtome</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Chryſ. con. <hi>2.</hi> de Lazar.</note> tels you, So long as wee are here, wee haue ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent hope, but being once gone; <hi>non eſt poſtea ſitum in nobis poenitere, neque commiſſa dilüere;</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:3259:19"/>It is not in our power afterwards to gaine re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, or to waſh away ſinne. No Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatorie can then purge vs:<note place="margin">Cypryan. ad Deme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r.</note> When <hi>Cyprian</hi> tels you, <hi>Hîc vita aut amittitur aut tenetur,</hi> Here life and happineſſe is either got or loſt. When <hi>Epiphanius</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">Epipha. cont. haereſ. lib. <hi>2.</hi> To. <hi>1.</hi> hareſ. <hi>59.</hi>
               </note> tels you; After this life is ended, <hi>Impletum eſt tempus, certamen perfectum euacua tum eſt ſtadium, et coronae datae ſunt;</hi> The time is fulfilled, the combate ended, the race is runne, and the crownes giuen. When
<hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">Aug. ad Mac. Epiſt.
<hi>54.</hi>
               </note> tels you, Of amendment of manners, there is no place but in this life; For this life being ended, <hi>Quiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> id habebit, quod in hâc ſibi conquiſiuit,</hi> Euery man ſhall haue that, which hee hath gained in this life. Seeke not, expect not, hope not for God when thou art dead, if thou caredſt not to finde him when thou wert aliue.</p>
            <p>And as we muſt ſeeke him onely in this life, ſo muſt we ſeeke him early in this life, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 21.12. <hi>The morning comes, and alſo the night; if you will ſeeke, ſeeke.</hi> If euer you meane to be doing, begin betimes. Imitate the holy women, <hi>Mar.</hi> 16.1. who ſought Chriſt earely, betimes in the <pb n="30" facs="tcp:3259:20"/>morning. Bee ſtirring in the prime of thy youth; giue God the may den head of thy life: there is no reaſon Satan ſhould haue the flowr of our daies, &amp; God the bran; that were to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the halt &amp; blind, and lame on his altar, if we begin not to ſeeke him, till we haue giuen ouer ſeeking all things elſe; yea, it is iuſt, that he in his age ſhould neuer finde him, who in his youth would neuer ſeeke him. Thus then, learne firſt to ſeeke him in due time.</p>
            <p>Secondly, remember alſo to ſeeke him in the right place. And where is that, ſaith <hi>Greg.</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">Greg. Moral. lib.
<hi>18.</hi> cap. <hi>15.</hi>
               </note> but <hi>In ſinu matris Eccleſiae,</hi> in the boſome of our mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Church. <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> ſought him in his graue, but S. <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">August. de temp. ſer. <hi>133.</hi>
               </note> reproues her,
<hi>Quid quaeris in tumulo, qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> adorare debes in coelo?</hi> why ſeekeſt thou him in the graue below, whom thou ſhouldeſt adore in the heauens aboue? <hi>Ioſeph</hi> and <hi>Mary</hi> ſought him in the crowde, and among their kindred; but <hi>S. Bernard</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunds, <hi>Quomodo, ô bone Ieſu, inter cognatos meos te inueniam, qui inter tuos minimè es inuentus?</hi> How, O ſweet Ieſus, ſhall I finde thee among my ſecular acquaintance, when thou wert not <pb n="31" facs="tcp:3259:20"/>found among thine owne naturall kinſmen? The Papiſts ſeeke him in their Images &amp; Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifixes; But the Scripture teacheth them, Chriſt which is the Author of verity, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be found in an Image, which is a teacher of lyes, <hi>Haba.</hi>
2.18. And who can thinke, the worke of man can conteine therein the Maker of man; or that that which is not quickned with life in it ſelfe, can hold Life it ſelfe that quickneth all things? If any man ſay, Lo here is Chriſt, or lo hee is there, beleeue him not. <hi>Math,</hi> 24.23.</p>
            <p>Come therefore to the Scriptures preached in the Church, there ſhall you finde him, and the Church too. For in a ſweet and harmoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous manner, wee finde the Scriptures in the Church, and the Church in the Scriptures: we finde the Scriptures in the Church; for to her are committed the Oracles of God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.2. And for this, ſhe is the ground &amp; pillar of truth, 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15. And in the Scriptures wee finde the Church, &amp; with the Church, Chriſt: Elſe would not
<hi>Augustine</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Auguſt. ad. Bonif. Epiſt.
<hi>50.</hi>
               </note> haue ſaid; <hi>In ſanctis Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bris, vbi manifestatur dominus Ieſus, ibi et eius Eccleſia declaratur,</hi> In the holy Bookes, where <pb n="32" facs="tcp:3259:21"/>our Lord Chriſt is manifeſt, there is alſo decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red his holy Church.</p>
            <p>Come then to the Church, if you deſire to finde Chriſt. When
<hi>Ioſeph</hi> &amp; <hi>Mary</hi> had loſt him, after three dayes labour, at laſt they found him in the Temple, <hi>Luke</hi> 2.46. There is his Seate, and there he is ſtill, <hi>in medio Dictorum,</hi> in the middeſt of his Miniſters, to aide them in preaching, yea, and <hi>in medio Diſcipulorum,</hi> in the middeſt of his Diſciples, to heare them in praying. It is well noted by <hi>Rabanus, Amat medium Mediator Dei et hominum.</hi> The Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atour of God and man, loues the middle part alwaies. When he was borne, he was <hi>in medio iumentorum,</hi> in the midſt of the beaſts; when he was twelue yeeres old, hee was <hi>in medio Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorum,</hi> in the middeſt of the Doctors; vvhen he taught, he ſtood <hi>in medio Diſcipulorum,</hi> in the midſt of his Diſciples; when he dyed, he was
<hi>in medio Latronum,</hi> in the midſt of the Theeues: Now hee is in heauen, hee is <hi>in medio Ange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorum,</hi> in the midſt of his Angels; and yet alſo <hi>in medio Chriſtianorum,</hi> in the midſt of vs Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, according to that, <hi>Math.</hi> 18.20. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:3259:21"/>two or three are gathered together in my name, there am I in the middeſt of them. To this houſe then let vs come: For where ſhould we ſind one, but in his owne houſe?</p>
            <p>And therefore <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.7. when the Church demanded of Chriſt, <hi>Vbi paſcis, vbi cubas in me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridie?</hi> Where doſt thou feed, vvhere doſt thou lye at noone-day? ſhe receiued this anſwere, If thou knoweſt not, follow the footſteps of the flockes to the tents of the Shepheards. That is, ſaith<note n="t" place="margin">Hugo Card. in Cant.
<hi>1.7.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Hugo Cardinalis, Attende opera et affectus Ecleſiasticorum conuentuum;</hi> Looke vpon the actions &amp; affections or the Church aſſemblies; Or as<note n="u" place="margin">Lyra ad loc. Cant.
<hi>17.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Lyra, Abi poſt veſtigia fidelium ad ſedes Doctorum:</hi> Follow the footſteps of the faithfull, to the ſeates of the Doctors: As if he had ſaid, Goe to the Preachers which teach, &amp; the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full that heare, there thou ſhalt quickly &amp; eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly finde me.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, as we muſt ſeeke him in due time, and place fitting, ſo alſo in a right manner. And this is all in all: For though one keepe his
<hi>Quando,</hi> and his <hi>Vbi,</hi> and obſerue not his <hi>Sicut oportet,</hi> if he keepe time and place, and not the <pb n="34" facs="tcp:3259:22"/>right maner, he is neuer the better. Now this <hi>Sicut,</hi> comprehends ſundry other aduerbs, that muſt be obſcrued in ſeeking God.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Caſte,</hi> purely and chaſtly. Seeke God for himſelfe, not for ſiniſter cauſes, and by-re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects. <hi>Ieſum propter Ieſum,</hi> ſeeke IESVS for ſaluation by IESVS:<note n="x" place="margin">Aug. de verb. Dom. ſerm. <hi>49.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Quiſquis à Deo praeter Deum aliquid quaerit, non caſtè Deum quaerit:</hi> Whoſoeuer ſeekes any thing of God, but God himſelfe, ſeekes him not chaſtly, nor purely. If a woman loue her husband becauſe he is rich, her loue is not chaſt: for how would ſhe doc if he were made poore? If ſhe cleaue to him for his riches, <hi>Non maritum amat, ſed aurum mariti,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auguſt. vt ſuprà</note> Shee loues not him, but his gold. So hee which ſeekes God for promotion, for profit, for any thing ſaue onely for himſelfe, ſeekes him not right. This, ſaith
<hi>Bernard,</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">Bern. in Pſal. Qui habitat. ſer.</note> is ſingular grace, ſingular perfection, <hi>Non modò nil ſperare niſi ab eo, ſed nil quaerere niſi eum:</hi> Not onely to expect nothing but from him, but alſo to ſeeke nothing but euen him.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Veraciter,</hi> truly, not fictitiouſly and hypocritically. It is his promiſe, <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.29. <pb n="35" facs="tcp:3259:22"/>Thou ſhalt finde the Lord, if thou ſeeke him with thy whole heart, and with all thy ſoule: otherwiſe, wee haue no aſſurance to find him. When we ſeeke but in ſhew, we ſhal finde but in ſhew.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>Feruenter,</hi> zealouſly &amp; earneſtly: not ſuperficially and perfunctoriouſly, as if we were indifferent whether we found him or not: but as <hi>Salomons</hi> Schollers ſeekes for wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,
<hi>Prou.</hi> 2.4. Seeking him as for ſiluer, &amp; ſearching for him, as for hid treaſure. Or as <hi>Samſon</hi> ſought drinke, <hi>Iudg.</hi>
15.18. If thou giue me no water, I die for thirſt. So <hi>Auguſtine</hi> cryed<note n="z" place="margin">Auguſt. confeſ.</note>, <hi>Quicquid dare mihi vult Dominus meus, auferat totum, et ſe mihi det;</hi> What-euer my Lord will be pleaſed to giue mee, let him take all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and giue me himſelfe.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>Perſeueranter,</hi> with perſeuerance and continuance, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 105. Seeke the Lord and his ſtrength, ſeeke his face euermore. For when wee haue found him for one thing, yet may we miſſe him for another thing. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Auguſt. in Pſal. <hi>104.</hi>
               </note> ſaith, Our ſeeking for God, ſignifieth our louing of God. Now loue muſt <pb n="36" facs="tcp:3259:23"/>continue and increaſe, <hi>et amore creſcente, inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio creſcatinuenti:</hi> And as our loue increaſeth, ſo our ſeeking of him (though we haue found him) muſt increaſe too. And ſurely if our hearts be ſurely ſet on him, we ſhall haue little minde on any thing elſe.
<hi>Plutarch</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Plut. Moral. T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>2.</hi> pag. <hi>116.</hi>
               </note> tels how
<hi>Nicias</hi> a Painter, was ſo pleaſed with his owne worke, that he forgat many times his meats, &amp; would aske his ſeruants whether he had dined that day. So if our hearts be well fixt on God beauty, we ſhal minde nothing ſo much as en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quirie after him. And as <hi>Zacheus</hi> hauing found Chriſt, preſently gaue away halfe his wealth at one daſh,<note place="margin">Luk. 19.8.</note> as if now hee had meant neuer to regard the world; ſo when wee haue found God, we ſhall little regard any thing elſe, ſaue only to keepe and retaine him in our ſoules.</p>
            <p>Fiftly, <hi>vnicè,</hi> we muſt ſeeke and inquire for him, and him alone; <hi>Non aliud tanquam illum, non aliud praeter illum, non aliud poſt illum,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bernard</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Bern. ſer. <hi>2</hi> de alt. &amp; baſſ. cord.</note>, not any thing as him, not any thing beſide him, not any thing after him. As <hi>Iacob</hi> ſaid when he heard of his ſon <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> I haue e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, &amp;c. So when wee haue found Chriſt <pb n="37" facs="tcp:3259:23"/>our ſpirituall <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> we ſhould both think and ſay, I haue enough, I deſire no more: For
<hi>Aua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re,</hi> ſaith <hi>Auguſtin</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Aug. de verb. Apoſt. ſerm. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Quid tibi ſufficit, ſi non ſufficit Deus?</hi> Couetous wrecth! what will ſerue thy turne, if God be not enough for thee? There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Eaſt gate in <hi>Ezekiels</hi> temple, was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſhut, and muſt neuer bee opened, becauſe God went once thorow it, <hi>Ezek.</hi>
24.2. So the heart of a Chriſtian ſhould bee ſhut to all other obiects whatſoeuer, and be left open onely to Almighty God. And as they write of the
<hi>Cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torian</hi> Well<note n="e" place="margin">Vitr. lib. <hi>8</hi> cap.
<hi>3.</hi> Ouid. Metam.</note>:
<q>
                  <l>Clitorio quicunque ſitim de fonte lauârit,</l>
                  <l>Vina fugit, gaudet<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> meris abſtemius vndis.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Whoſoeuer dranke of that fountaine, could neuer abide to drinke wine after it: ſo we ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing taſted of the bleſſed waters of life flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from God himſelfe, we ſhould neuer deſire nor thirſt after the wines of fleſhly delights, but cheerefully reioyce &amp; ſay as the Church,
<hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduxit mè Rex in cellaria ſuâ</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cant. <hi>1.4.</hi>
               </note> The King hath brought me into his Wine-cellar; we will be glad and reioyce in thee, wee will remember thy loue more then wine.</p>
            <pb n="38" facs="tcp:3259:24"/>
            <p>Thus hee that ſeekes God, ſhall bee ſure to finde. But one thing wee muſt not forget to remember, that we can neuer ſeeke him, vnleſſe he firſt of al finde vs; for of our ſelues we haue no power, nor will to looke after him, vntil he hath moued vs, and rowzed vs vp to it. As all ſeeking is vaine, vnleſſe we ſeeke him? ſo all ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of him is in vaine, vnleſſe he finde vs. <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Bern. de dilig. Deo.</note> doubted not to ſay, <hi>Nemo, Domine, te quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rere valet, niſi qui prius inuenerit:</hi> No man, O Lord, can ſeeke thee, but hee who hath firſt found thee. Wouldſt thou be found of vs? The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> firſt doe thou finde vs. <hi>Potes quaeri et inueniri, non tamen prae ueniri:</hi> Thou maiſt be ſought and found of vs, but not till thou haſt ſought and found out vs thy ſelfe <hi>Dauid Pſal.</hi> 88.13. ſaid, Hee would preuent God with his prayer; but God muſt firſt preuent
<hi>Dauid</hi> with his Spirit: he is firſt to euery man, no man firſt to him.</p>
            <p>And ſurely hence it is, that there bee ſo few that truely ſeeke God; many that ſeeke the world and themſelues: ſome that ſeeke they know not what. Either men heare not the voice of God ſpeaking vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but ſuffocate <pb n="39" facs="tcp:3259:24"/>and choake vp the good motions of the Spirit, or elſe giue eare to the voice of the world, hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kening rather to the Marchants of <hi>Ianus,</hi> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Quaerenda pecunia primùm eſt:</hi> Seeke money before vertue, rather then to the Miniſters of IESVS, ſpeaking, <hi>Quaerite primùm Regnum Dei, Math.</hi> 6.33. Seeke yee firſt the Kingdome of God. Neuer Citie, neuer Church had more ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation to ſeeke God then this; and yet, O how few doe practiſe it aright!
<hi>Pliny</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Plin. lib. <hi>14.</hi> in Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oem.</note> ſaith, There are ſome trees which are called <hi>Arbores indociles, quae in alienas non co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meant terras:</hi> indo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible trees, that will bee taught to growe no where, but where they were firſt bred. Doe not thinke me blind, if I tell you I ſee many wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in the Garden of this Citie like trees, that are indocible to any thing ſaue to the courſe they haue bin bred in, trading for money, and ſeeking for gaine. For the purchaſe of heauen, by expence of earthly pelfe; this Marchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize we cannot teach them, though we labour it neuer ſo much. This they thinke is an vnpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable ſtudie, they deſire not to be conuerſant in it. The common ſearch is, <hi>Quis oſtendet no <pb n="40" facs="tcp:3259:25"/>bis bona? Pſal.</hi>
4.6. Whither ſhall we goe for a good bargaine? where ſhall wee finde a good purchaſe?</p>
            <p>And it were infinite to reckon vp other ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, who greedily purſue euery man his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per delight. Onely God among them left out, and either not ſought for at all, or elſe in the laſt place, when wee are able to ſeeke nothing elſe. And yet if we ſhould ſpend all our life in ſeeking out ſeuerall delights, peraduenture all would proue but
<hi>infructuoſus labor,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. ad Lar. Epiſt.
<hi>82.</hi>
               </note> vnprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble paine: or if we ſhould find them, all would be but <hi>fallax ſuauitas,</hi> deceitfull ſweetneſſe, like S.
<hi>Iohns</hi> booke,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Reu.</hi> 10.9.</note> ſweet as honey in the mouth, &amp; bitter as gall in the belly. Onely God is worth the finding; onely, God will not fruſtrate our ſeeking; ſo is his promiſe: So our Text tels vs, <hi>If ye ſeeke him, he will be found of you.</hi> And this is the ſecond point, The wages. We haue heard what is the worke, to ſeeke God; now are we come to the wages, The finding of him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He will be found of you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is nothing ſo acceptable to a man, as not to bee fruſtrate in his hope &amp; expectation. <pb n="41" facs="tcp:3259:25"/>
               <hi>Multos expertus ſum, qui fallere volunt,</hi> ſaith <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Aug. conf. lib. <hi>10.</hi> cap. <hi>23.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>qui autem falli neminem:</hi> I haue had tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all of many that would deceiue, but neuer of any that would be deceiued. Nothing ſo wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come to a ſeeker, as to finde; but to finde God, is to a Chriſtian more pleaſing, then when the Mariner findes the ſhore, the Marchantrich wares, the labourer his hire, the Traueller his iourneyes end. For God is the Centre to which all hearts mooue, and when they are come to him, they reſt as being fully ſatisfied.</p>
            <p>Now there is <hi>2.</hi> degrees of finding God; One in this life, the other in the life to come: In this world he is found <hi>per fidem,</hi> by faith; in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther world, <hi>per ſpeciem,</hi> by ſight: In this world we finde him by faith: for, <hi>credere, inueniſſe eſt, Bern.</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Bern. in Cant. ſer. <hi>76.</hi>
               </note> To beleeue, is to haue found him; but this giues vs not full content, therefore we ſeek him ſtill;
<hi>I am quippe illum inuenit fides, ſed adbuc illum quaerit ſpes,</hi> ſaith <hi>Aug.</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Aug. in Pſal.
<hi>104.</hi>
               </note> Faith hath found him here, but hope lookes to finde him better hereafter: And loue doth both theſe, <hi>Charitas et inuenit eum per ſidem, et eum quaer it habere per ſpeciem:</hi> Charity hath both found him here by <pb n="42" facs="tcp:3259:26"/>faith, and yet further ſeekes for him by ſight. And though he dwels in an inacceſſible light, whither no man can enter, 1.
<hi>Tim.</hi> 6.16. yet faith pryeth and preſſeth in vnto him, in his moſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret cloſet of glory: yea, <hi>Quid non inuenit fides?</hi> ſaith <hi>Bernard.</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Bern. in Cant. ſer.
<hi>76.</hi>
               </note> What will not faith finde out? <hi>Attingit inacceſſa, deprehendit ignota, &amp;c.</hi> It rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth to things inacceſſible, it findes out things vnvtterable, comprehends things vnmeaſura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, apprehends things vnapproachable; yea, it incloſeth within the large boſome of it, euen Eternity it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>The benefits which faith gaines by finding God in this life, are two. 1. Remiſſion of ſins. 2. Imputation of righteouſneſſe. Firſt, remiſſion of ſinnes, for it tranſlates a man from
<hi>Moſes</hi> to the <hi>Meſsias;</hi> from the Law condemning, to the Goſpell abſoluing. <hi>Zacharias</hi> was ſtricken dumbe, when Chriſt was to be borne, <hi>Luk.</hi> 1.20. in token that the Law was to beſilent whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Goſpell ſhould be preached. And as the womans accuſers brought her to Chriſt, and afterwards dropt away and left none but them two alone,
<hi>Iohn</hi> 8.9. <hi>Remanſit magna miſeria &amp; <pb n="43" facs="tcp:3259:26"/>magnamiſericordia,</hi> ſaith <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Aug. in Pſal.</note> There remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned no body, but miſery and mercy together: So when the Law hath ſchooled vs with the rod of terror, it atlaſt brings vs to Chriſt, the Prince of Peace, &amp; there we finde our iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties forgiuen, and our conſciences at quiet.</p>
            <p>So alſo it gaines vs imputation of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes: For Chriſt which dwels in our hearts by faith, <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.17. communicates his gifts and graces where he dwels. So that what is his, is ours, that is, righteouſnes; as once what vvas ours, was made his, that is, ſinne. And ſurely, ſaith <hi>Bernard,</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">Bern. Epist.
<hi>190.</hi>
               </note> This righteouſneſſe, is <hi>Tutior do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nata, quàm innata:</hi> More ſafe when it is giuen vs, then ſauing when it is wrought by vs: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, this may haue glory, but not before God. No,
<hi>Ea Deum perfecta, &amp; omnimoda gloriatio eſt in Deo,</hi> ſaith
<hi>S. Baſil,</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">Baſil. ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, de humilit.</note> That is perfect &amp; ſound glorying in the ſight of God, when a man feeles himſelfe deſtitute of true righteouſneſſe, and expects alone by faith to receiue righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe from God. Thus we finde him by faith in this world.</p>
            <p>Secondly, hope findes him by ſight in the <pb n="44" facs="tcp:3259:27"/>world to come: and this is truely to find him, becauſe then we ſhall enioy him; he ſhall bee with vs, and in vs, yea, all in all, 1.
<hi>Cor.</hi> 15.28. What is all in all? ſaith <hi>S. Aug.</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">Aug. de verb. Apoſt. ſerm. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Quic quid hic quaerebas, quic quid hic promagno habebas, ipſe ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi erit:</hi> Whatſoeuer here thou haſt ſought af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, whatſoeuer heere thou haſt admired and purſued, that ſhall God bee there vnto thee. What? was it meate &amp; drinke thou hungredſt after? Why, <hi>Erit tibi cibus &amp; potus:</hi> God ſhall bee meate and drinke vnto thee: was it glory and preferment thou gapedſt after? God ſhall be that vnto thee too. It may bee thou wert couetous, and couldſt not be ſatisfied with mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney? <hi>Auare<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> quid tibi ſufficit, ſi Deus ipſe non ſufficit?</hi> O couetous wretch! what will bee i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for thee, if hauing found God, thou yet findeſt thy ſelfe empty? Heere wee are at the Center; here, at the Well-head; heere wee may drink, &amp; fill all the empty corners of our heart, which could neuer bee ſatisfied in this world before.</p>
            <p>If this will not incourage vs to ſeeke him, what will? Thus much is certaine: If we ſeeke <pb n="45" facs="tcp:3259:27"/>him not to finde him, wee forſake him &amp; loſe him. And that is the thing which he threatens vs, in the next words:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If ye forſake him, he will forſake you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hitherto we haue beene allured with ſweet promiſes, now he comes to ſeuere menacing: And it is worth the noting; here are two allu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ring promiſes, for one terrifying threat. Two for one, and thoſe in the firſt place; which ſhewes how milde, how gracious our God is; and how vnwilling to vſe iuſtice, if mercy would preuaile.</p>
            <p>In this third member, conſider <hi>culpa</hi> &amp;
<hi>poena:</hi> the finne, and the penalty; The ſin, to forſake God; The penalty, to be forſaken of God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If ye forſake him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the firſt, Forſaking of God: One would thinke, that man, the Prince of vnderſtanding and reaſon, ſhould neuer be ſo ſubiect to blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and error, as to forſake God, which is the very ſoule of bliſſe, and bliſſe of the ſoule. <hi>I am the Way, the Truth, and the Life,</hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 14.16. Whither wouldſt thou goe, ſaith <hi>Aug?</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Aug. hom. <hi>34.</hi> inter.
<hi>50.</hi>
               </note> Chriſt is the Truth, where wouldſt thou tarry?
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:3259:28"/>He is the Life, by what path woldſt thou trace? He is the Way. Doth any man thinke to gaine life by running from it?<note place="margin">Hugo Card. in Mat. <hi>24.</hi>
               </note> ſaith <hi>Hugo Card.</hi> Yet ſuch is the madnes of man ſince the Fall, that hee hath no minde to draw neere to God; but as <hi>Adam</hi> hid himſelfe in the thickeſt of Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe from the knowledge of God: ſo his heires deſire to conceale themſelues in the miſts and foggynes of carnall delights, from the God of knowledge. As ſore eyes deſire not to behold the Sunne: ſo a guilty conſcience hath no mind to draw neere to God, but rather <hi>Cain</hi>-like to depart from the preſence of the Lord, <hi>Gen.</hi> 4.16 into the Land of
<hi>Nod,</hi> the land of baniſhment, to liue in perpetuall exile from all grace and goodneſſe.</p>
            <p>And this would all men doe, were there not appointed of God, Miniſters to call vpon vs, the Word whereby to call, and a Church whereinto to call vs; that we may find God for grace here, and glory hereafter. Although in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, no ſinne be comparable to this, that the creature ſhould fall away &amp; depart from the Creator.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.4.</note> Heare the Prophets, They haue forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken <pb n="47" facs="tcp:3259:28"/>the Lord, they haue prouoked the Holy one of <hi>Iſrael</hi> to anger, they haue gone backe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward. And <hi>Ier.</hi> 2.19. It is an euill thing and a bitter, that thou haſt forſake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Lord thy God, and that his feare is not in thee. And
<hi>S. Peter,</hi> 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.21. It had beene better not to haue knowne the Word of Truth, then hauing ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted of it, to fall away into error. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Aquinas</hi> ſ ſaith,<note place="margin">Aquin.
<hi>2.</hi> ſecun. quaeſt. <hi>12.</hi> a. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> Though Apoſtaſie be not infidelitie properly, yet is it <hi>circumſtantia aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nans eam,</hi> a circumſtance aggrauating it, and making it worſe. And it muſt needs bee ſo. For God is <hi>Summum Bonum,</hi> the neerer a man comes to God, the neerer hee is to goodneſſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and the further a man departs from him, the further he is from goodneſſe. Now as
<hi>Ambr.</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">Ambr. in Pſal. <hi>118.</hi> ſer.
<hi>15.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Non interuallo locorum Deus relinquitur, ſed pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitate morum:</hi> God is not forſaken by diſtance of place, but by lewdnes of manners. And he forſakes God moſt, that is fartheſt from good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
            <p>And yet for all this, though by the Word &amp; Sacraments, men are drawne to God, many regard not to come at all, or elſe beeing once
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:3259:29"/>come, depart from him againe; cleauing to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other obiect, as the Prodigall to the Hog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard, <hi>Luk.</hi> 15.15. embracing <hi>vitreum, non ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Margaritum;</hi> a gliſtring vanity, in ſtead of celeſtiall verity.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Abulenſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ad loc.</note> The wayes wherby men more particularly fall from God, are Foure.</p>
            <p>Firſt, as <hi>Toſtatus</hi> well notes, <hi>de relinquendo le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem Dei,</hi> by forſaking Gods Law, that is, his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice and worſhip eſtabliſhed in the Church. By Religion we are <hi>Deoreligati,</hi> bound &amp; tyed vnto God. Whereupon it is, that ſuch as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake Religion, ſaith <hi>Lactan.</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">Lact. Inſt. lib. <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> are compared <hi>fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lijs abdicatis, aut ſeruis fugitiuis,</hi> either to forlorn ſonnes, or fugitiue ſeruants, wherof one ſeekes not to his father, nor the other to his Maſter.</p>
            <p>I truſt there is no neceſſity that I ſhould ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort you to conſtancy in Religion; you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but ſee, how infinitely God hath bleſſed this Land ſince the Goſpell flouriſhed: your bodies haue felt it in caſe and pleaſure; your ſoules taſted of it in grace and vertue; your eſtates growne fat by it, in plenty and abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance; your hearts been ioyed with it, in peace <pb n="49" facs="tcp:3259:29"/>and proſperity. Should wee now feare a defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction? What though ſome few ſtraggling frogs haue been catched in the net of a Popiſh Fiſher? What is this to the See of our Church? What maruell, though ſome few ſeeme to fall to the Popiſh religion, that were neuer of any before? Certainely, I preſume of this place, this City, this Kingdome, that you would deſire ra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther to periſh out of the world, then that true Religion ſhould periſh out of the Church.</p>
            <p>And for our comfort, wee haue his Maieſty for our patterne; who as his iudgement and learning informes him againſt falſhood: ſo his affections &amp; deſires confirme him to the truth: That ſhould
<hi>Rome,</hi> and all <hi>Romaniſts</hi> come to him, and make it a requeſt, to mingle their old dregs with our pure Water of life; as once they came to <hi>Valentinian,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amb. orat. de obit. Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len.</note> to intreat for <hi>Templorumiura, ſacerdotiorum prophana priuile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gia:</hi> The old ceremonies of Idolatrous Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, prophane priuiledges of their ſuperſtitious Prieſthood: He would vndoubtedly anſwere them, as that famous <hi>Valentinian</hi> did; <hi>Quod pius frater eripuit, quomodò à me putatis eſſe redden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:3259:30"/>quum in eo Religio laedatur &amp; frater?</hi> That which my Brother King <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixt, (let meadde my Siſter too, Queene
<hi>Elizabeth</hi> of famous memory) did take away, how would you haue me to reſtore again, conſidering, that therein I ſhould wrong Religion, &amp; them too? Certainely, wee ſhould be very diſloyall to his Maieſty, if wee ſhould with a needleſſe feare perplexe our ſelues with that, wherein wee ought to beleeue him moſt firme and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant.</p>
            <p>What then, ſhall we be ſecure? No; but the more that Satan ſtriues to ſupplant vs, the fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer footing let vs take. If Prieſts and Ieſuites ſwarme in houſes, let vs ſo much more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoutely flocke together in Churches. If they ſeduce the wauering, let vs co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firme the weake. As they plod for Antichriſt, let vs take paines for Chriſt.
<hi>Plut.</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Plut. lib. de vtilit. ab hoſt. cap.</note> tels vs, that it is a wiſemans part to get commodity, euen from an enemie. Let vs ſtriue to gaine thus much from them, to double our diligence in the preaching and practiſing of Religion: and then wee neede not feare forſaking of God, by falling from <pb n="51" facs="tcp:3259:30"/>Religion.<note place="margin">Et reuera cùm quae<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> nouitas e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bullit, ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tim cernitur frumentoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> grauitas, et leuitas pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learum. Vincent. contra Haeriſs.</note> It may be now is a time wherein God would diſcerne between
<hi>frumentorum grauitas, &amp; leuitas palearum,</hi> as <hi>Cyprian</hi> and
<hi>Vincentius</hi> ſpeake: the weight and flowrineſſe of good corne, which he reſerues for his Garner; and the lightneſſe and vnprofitableneſſe of chaffe, which he determines for hell fire. <hi>Hee that is faithfull vnto the death, ſhall bee ſure to inioy the Crowne of Life.</hi> Reu. 2.10.</p>
            <p>The ſecond way whereby men forſake God, is, by forſaking his Miniſtry, in withdrawing their maintenance and Liuelode from them. The Miniſtry is <hi>Seminarium Eccleſiae:</hi> The Churches ſeed-plot: deſtroy that, and farewell Religion. And deſtroyed it will be, if not che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed and maintayned by ſufficient meanes. O the damned ſinne of Sacriledge! how it ſtrikes as the roote of Religion, &amp; aimes at the Maieſtie of God himſelfe!<note place="margin">Lact. Inſt. lib. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> And therefore <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctantius</hi> notes, That God puniſhed it among the Heathens, becauſe (though hee cared not for any iniurie done to an Idoll, yet) he would make men afraid of withdrawing any thing from him, whom they in their blind iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <pb n="52" facs="tcp:3259:31"/>tooke for the true God. And this was vſuall.<note place="margin">Lucan.</note>
            </p>
            <q>—Quis enim laeſos impunè putaret eſſe deos?</q>
            <p>Who euer ſaw the gods ſpoyled &amp; robbed, without condigne puniſhment? And the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of the Miniſtry is Gods maintenance; becauſe it ſerues for the vpholding his imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate ſeruice and worſhip.</p>
            <p>It is true,<note place="margin">Hugo Card. in Iſa.
<hi>49.23.</hi>
               </note> I grant, that <hi>Hugo Cardinalis</hi> notes, that the reuenews of the Clergy is the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches food, and when the Church was young like a childe, it ouer-ate it ſelfe, and ſurfeited. But as ſurfeiting &amp; diſeaſes of oppletion muſt be cured with purging: ſo hath this courſe been taken, and our Church ouer-purged this way, that ſhe is now on the other ſide in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of a Conſumption through too much eua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuation. I know not how that ſame <hi>auri ſacra fames;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Virgil.</note> or <hi>auri ſacri fames</hi> hath growne into eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry mans ſtomacke, that hee thinkes all is well gotten, which is pilfered from the Church.</p>
            <p>I know where I am, and to whom I ſpeake. I ſuppoſe it is farre from the minde of this City <pb n="53" facs="tcp:3259:31"/>to forſake God or Religion, by withdrawing the Miniſteriall maintenance. I know, you giue much, and freely, to painefull and labori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous men. You loue (I confeſſe) our preaching, and will countenance it with your preſence &amp; purſes; but giue mee leaue, I beſeech you, to tell, that there be in this City, who like not of vs, becauſe (though wee preach, yet) wee can worke no Miracles. How is that? Becauſe (in plaine Engliſh) wee cannot liue now as our Predeceſſors did an hundred yeeres agoe, of twenty or thirty pounds a yeere; which to doe, in my iudgement, were no leſſe then a Miracle. And theſe men can thinke it fit to raiſe the fee of euery the meaneſt officer, and to tye the Miniſter to his old ſtint, as if his calling were not worth the vpholding.</p>
            <p>Others there he, who are ſo far from giuing any thing that is their owne, that they with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold what is the Miniſters owne. Laſtly, ſome, who had rather giue it to any, then their owne Paſtor. I would there were more diſcretion on euery ſide: I would not haue it ſpoken of this City, as it was ſpoken of <hi>Sylla,</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Plut. in Sylla.</note> 
               <hi>Multa eri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piebat, <pb n="54" facs="tcp:3259:32"/>donabat plura:</hi> He iniuriouſly wreſted many things from the right owners, and gaue away prodigally much vnto others; inſomuch as it was a great queſtion,
<hi>Naturá ne contemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor hominum, an adulator fuerit?</hi> Whether natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally he were more a ſcorner or flatterer of me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. It would much impeach the wiſedome of this City, to bee in this various humour, to offer iniury to one, and ſhew courteſie to another. I ſpeake not in mine owne behalfe; I thanke God; it is a part of my happineſſe, that my lot hath falne in ſuch a place, as hitherto hath afforded mee loue and courteſie, not neglect and vnkindneſſe; and I wiſh it had beene ſo with others alſo.</p>
            <p>But one thing I beſeech you giue mee leaue to informe you in: I am bound to wiſh well to the Church in generall, but ſpecially in this City, where I am like to liue (for ought I know) and to ſpend my dayes; I would not conceale any thing which might doe good. <hi>Miſer eſt Imperator apud quem vera reticentur:</hi> as he ſaid, That Prince, that State is in an euill caſe, from whom the truth is concealed.<note n="c" place="margin">Iul. Capit. Gard. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> You haue here <pb n="55" facs="tcp:3259:32"/>in this City, many that feede vpon your boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, who haue Liuings, yea, charge of ſoules of their owne abroade in the Countrey. Do you thinke you doe well, to giue entertainment to theſe men? When you take the next courſe to pull downe Religion, and to make their peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple forſake God, as they haue forſaken their people? Will you maintaine a man in the neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect of his owne charge? Can it be honeſty for any mans wife, to loue another womans husband? Shall that bee accounted lawfull among vs, which Scriptures, Councels, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, Canons, Papiſts, Browniſts, and all the world condemnes?</p>
            <p>O bee aduiſed in your charity! Spoyle not ſo excellent a worke in the manner of doing. There are ynow will attend you, as ſufficient as theſe. Thinke hereon, I beſeech you, and the Lord giue you vnderſtanding in all things.</p>
            <p>The third way whereby men forſake God, is, By vnthankfulneſſe. For that vice denies God, and withdrawes mans heart from the Lord: <hi>Peremptoriares eſt ingratitudo, hostis gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae, inimica ſalutis,</hi> ſaith <hi>Bern.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bern. ſer.
<hi>3.</hi> de ſept. pan.</note> d Ingratitude is <pb n="56" facs="tcp:3259:33"/>a killing ſinne, an enemy to grace, a foe to ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation. Yea it is a parching &amp; a nipping wind, drying vp the fountaine of mercy &amp; compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. It vtterly ſeparates God and man aſunder: for by it wee runne from him, as the Prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall from his father, and he departs from vs, as the life from the dying limbes.</p>
            <p>It were a ſhame that wee ſhould be charged with this ſinne, who of all people ſhould bee fartheſt from it. And yet we muſt confeſſe, we haue ill requited the Lord for his mercies. It is not long, ſince it pleaſed him to open the windowes of Heauen, and to ſend vs abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of Corne: which, when it ſhould haue moued thankefulnes; it procured murmuring and complayning on all ſides. Since, wee ſee, how the Lord hath withdrawne his hand, cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtened vs with penurie; as appeares (among many other ſenſible arguments) by the infinite number of Poore, ſwarming in the ſtreets; for whom, had not ſome good order beene taken by the Lord Maior and the graue Senators of the Citie; men ſhould not haue quietly paſſed one by another.</p>
            <pb n="57" facs="tcp:3259:33"/>
            <p>So wee haue long enioyed a happy Peace, which is indeede, the greateſt mercy that Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen can communicate to earth: And yet may we not heare ſome weary of eaſe, and wiſhing for Warre? Warre, the firebrand of the world, the enemy of content, and bane of hearts-eaſe. Whereby,
<q>
                  <l>Nobilitas cum plebe perit,<note place="margin">Lucan.</note> laté<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> vagatur</l>
                  <l>Enſis, &amp; ànullo reuocatum eſt pectore ferrum.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Ruines &amp; deſtructions come vpon all ſtates of men. Let me tell you a ſtory; It is of <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> that famous, but vnfortunate Emperour Hee,<note place="margin">Othe. Friſide geſt. Fred. lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap.</note> in his young yeeres comming into <hi>Sax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ony,</hi> obſeruing the ſtrength and largeneſſe of that Countrey; vauntingly and vainely ſaid, He wondred, that in ſo large a Continent as was his Empire, none could be found to rebell, againſt whom he might exerciſe his proweſſe and valour. It was not long, before hee had obiects inow to try his ſtrength vpon: for the Pope excommunicating him, his Subiects fell away from him, &amp; his ſon roſe vp in armes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, and miſery and beggery vvas his end. Take heed, be not weary of Peace; <hi>Mala <pb n="58" facs="tcp:3259:34"/>vota ſunt,</hi> ſaith <hi>Auguſt. optare habere quem oderis, vt eſſe poſſit que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vincas:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. de Ciu. Dei, lib.
<hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>15.</hi>
               </note> It is bad wiſhing ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to bee thine aduerſary, in hope thereby to make thy ſelfe a conquerer.</p>
            <p>The fourth way, wherby men forſake God, is, by prophaneneſſe, when they fall to imbrace the world, and ſucke the fulſome ſweet plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of it;<note place="margin">a Greg. in Euang. hom.
<hi>15.</hi>
               </note> As if it were poſſible, <hi>Et hîc gaude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re cum ſeculo, et illic regnare cum Chriſto:</hi> Here, to reuell it with the world, and hereafter to reigne with Chriſt. Such was <hi>Demas,</hi> who for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooke <hi>Pauls</hi> company, and Chriſts ſeruice, to embrace this preſent world, 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.10. Theſe men are compared to
<hi>Lots</hi> wife, who beeing fetched out by the Angels from <hi>Sodom,</hi> loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked backe, and was turned into a Piller of Salt, <hi>Gen.</hi> 19.26.
<hi>Saint Auguſtine</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Aug. de Ciu. lib.
<hi>16.</hi> cap. <hi>30.</hi>
               </note> She was tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into a Piller of Salt, to ſeaſon all others by her example, that they looke not backe to the
<hi>Sodom</hi> of this world, when they haue beene called from thence by the Miniſters, Gods An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels. But <hi>S. Peter</hi> compareth prophane men to worſe things, <hi>viz.</hi> to Dogs and Swine: For they verifie the Prouerbe, The Dog is returned <pb n="59" facs="tcp:3259:34"/>to his vomite, and the Sow that was waſhed, to her wallowing in the mire, 2. <hi>Peter</hi> 2.22. Men in Baptiſme are waſhed &amp; made cleane, and in aſſociating themſelues to the congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>nequitiam de qua malè ſaciati fuerant, confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendo proijciunt,</hi> faith S. <hi>Gregory:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Greg. Paſt. cur. par. <hi>3.</hi> adm. <hi>31.</hi>
               </note> they vnloade their ſtomackes of ſin by hearty confeſſion; but falling afterwards to prophaneneſſe, they reſume their old filth and garbage, and defile themſelues in the dirt of iniquity. A very beaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly courſe, and much to bee deteſted. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, let vs take heede of this, it doubles our damnation; and much better it had beene for vs not to haue knowne the truth, then hauing knowne it, to runne into error. No comfort, but all miſery gained this way; for by forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king God, he forſakes vs. And that is the pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He will forſake you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No miſery vnder heauen, nor vnder earth neither, ſhould we goe as low as hell, to this, that God ſhold forſake vs. If wealth, preferme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, honour, life, or whatſoeuer elſe ſhould forſake vs, it were no great matter, God is more then al <pb n="60" facs="tcp:3259:35"/>theſe; and ſo long as he is with vs, we cannot be but well. When the Heathens iudged the Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s vnhappy foe ſuffring pouerty, ſpoile, baniſhment, &amp;c. S.
<hi>Auguſtine</hi> anſweres, <hi>Hoc ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nè miſerrimum eſſet,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. de ciu. Dei, lib. <hi>1.</hi> cap.
<hi>14.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſi aliquò duci potuerunt, vbi Deum ſuum non inuenirent:</hi> Now ſurely their caſe were miſerable, if they could bee carried any whither where they might not finde their God. But ſo long as God is with them, they cannot be vnhappy.</p>
            <p>O but when God is gone from a man, his caſe is moſt wretched; for then euery thing becomes his enemy, yea, his Maſter and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querour. A haire in ones milke, may bee our bane, as it was with that Senator; a flie in the ayre may choake vs, as it was with Pope <hi>Adri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Naucler vr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpergenſ.</note> And what is leſſe then theſe, if there be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing, may doe more then theſe, if it were poſſible, when God hath forſaken vs, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawne his ſauing health from vs. What ſhall I ſay? men and Angels cannot expreſſe the horrour and miſery which they are open to, whom God hath forſaken.</p>
            <p>Sec here Gods iuſtice, how hee puniſheth <hi>in
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:3259:35"/>analogo!</hi> There is beauty and comelineſſe in all his workes; his very iuſtice ſhines glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, in the exerciſe of it. He forſakes ſuch as forſake him: So he proportions his puniſhment to the ſinne. See it in others: <hi>Pharaoh</hi> ſlew the Male childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Iſraelites; therfore his firſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borne muſt dye, <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.29. He drowned them in the greene riuer: God deſtroyes him in the red Sea. The Sodomites burne with vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall luſt; <hi>Ergo,</hi> they muſt be burned with ſupernaturall fire, <hi>Gen.</hi> 19.24. <hi>Adonibezek</hi> cuts off the thumbes and toes of 70. Kings; <hi>Ergo, Iudah</hi> muſt cut off his for it in the end, <hi>Iudg.</hi> 1.6. <hi>Dauid</hi> kills <hi>Vriah</hi> with the edge of the ſword; <hi>Ergo,</hi> the ſword muſt neuer depart from his houſe, 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 12.10. <hi>Iezabel</hi> ſhed <hi>Naboths</hi> bloud by dogged men; <hi>Ergo,</hi> her bloud in the ſame place, muſt be licked vp of dogs, 2. <hi>King.</hi> 9.36. <hi>Diues</hi> would not giue
<hi>Lazarus</hi> a crumme of bred; <hi>Ergo, Lazarus</hi> muſt not giue him a drop of water, <hi>Luke</hi> 16.25. <hi>Iulian,</hi> &amp; <hi>Foelix</hi> his companion, ſpeake diſdainfully of Chriſt, and miſuſe his ſacred Ornaments; One ſaid of the Church veſſels, <hi>En, qualibus vaſis miniſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur <pb n="62" facs="tcp:3259:36"/>Mariae Filio:</hi> See what veſſels
<hi>Maries</hi> Son is ſerued in. He that vented this, preſently vents all his bloud at his mouth, &amp; dyes. The other piſſeth againſt the Communion Table: hee therefore could neuer piſſe more, but voide his excrements at his mouth.<note place="margin">Theod. hiſt. Eccl. lib.
<hi>3.</hi> cap. <hi>12.13.</hi>
               </note> One in <hi>Cyprians</hi> time denied Chriſt, he is therefore preſently ſtricken dumbe:<note place="margin">Cipr. de lapſ.</note> 
               <hi>Poena inde caepit, vnde caepit et crime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> ſaith
<hi>Cpyrian</hi> There began his torment, where began his ſinne. And vnworthy was that mouth e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer after to open, which had euer vſed it ſelfe to deny Chriſt. Infinite examples are extant for this point: Let vs feare God and honour him, and then wee neede feare nothing elſe: e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery thing ſhall proſper with vs.</p>
            <p>Againe note heere, that if God forſake vs, it is,<note place="margin">Aug. ſer. <hi>22.</hi> de temp.</note> becauſe wee firſt forſake him. This <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stine</hi> firmely reſolues on, and would haue eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man beleeue, <hi>Quia Deus nunquam deſerit ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minem, niſi priùs ab homine deſeratur:</hi> God neuer forſakes man, till man hath firſt forſaken him. See his longanimitie! Shall wed beginne with him? Shall we prouoke him to anger? Are we ſtronger then hee? As yet he hath not forſaken <pb n="63" facs="tcp:3259:36"/>vs. Nay, he hath declared himſelfe to be more with vs, then with any nation beſide. When warre and diſcord, famine and ſword, plague and mortality hath beene round about vs, yet we haue beene in ſafety, farre from the reach and contagion of any.</p>
            <p>What remaineth, but that we remember e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery man to come neerer vnto him: <hi>Ecce, qui elongant, ſe à te peribunt. Pſal.</hi>
73.27. Behold, they which goe far away from thee, ſhall periſh.</p>
            <p>Let vs draw neere him in grace, ſo ſhall wee draw neere him in glory. Still let vs recount the Text, <hi>He is with vs, if we be with him.</hi> He grant that wee may bee with him in knowledge, in loue; and then hee will be with vs in his prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction on earth, and in felicity in Heauen. Vnto which hee vouchſafe to bring vs in his appointed time, for Ieſus Chriſt his ſake; To whom with the Father, &amp;c.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
